Ron Baker fonds
Simon Fraser University Archives and Records Management Department
Ron Baker fonds
1948 - 1997
F-34
Q99982722
75 cm of textual records 27 photographs: slides 7 photographs: prints 7 postcards
Simon Fraser University Archives and Records Management Department Maggie Benston Student Services Building, Rm. 0400 8888 University Dr. Burnaby British Columbia Canada V5A 1S6 Telephone: 778.782.3805 Email: archives@sfu.ca http://www.sfu.ca/archives
PHYSICAL DESCRIPTION: 27 photographs: slides, 7 photographs: prints located in SMI room 35-4-3
Baker, Ron
Ronald “Ron” James Baker was the first faculty member hired by President Patrick McTaggart-Cowan for the new Simon Fraser University (SFU) in 1964. Baker served as the university's Director of Academic Planning and as the first head of the English Department. He remained at SFU until 1969, when he was appointed to be the first president of the new University of Prince Edward Island.
Baker was born in London, England, on August 24, 1924, to James “Jim” Herbert Walter and Ethel Frances Baker (nee Miller). He served with the Royal Air Force (1943-1947), during which time he trained in Manitoba. After the war, in 1947, he immigrated to Canada.
Baker married Helen “Jo” Gillespie Elder [ca. 1947]; they would have 5 children (Sharon Ann, Lynn Frances, Ian James, Sarah Jane, and Katherine Jean). In 1975, he married Frances Marilyn Frazer (1932-2010), with whom he had one son, Ralph Edward “Ted.”
Baker graduated from the University of British Columbia (UBC) with a Bachelor of Arts in 1951 and a Master of Arts in 1953, both in English. He went on to do graduate work in the School of Oriental and African Studies at the University of London (1954-1956). Baker had lectured in English during his undergraduate degree at UBC, and returned to the University to become an associate professor in 1962. While at UBC, Baker was involved in the production of John B. Macdonald’s report, Higher Education in British Columbia and a Plan for the Future (1962), which led directly to the development of a second university (SFU) in the Lower Mainland.
In 1964, Baker became the first faculty member hired by President Patrick McTaggart-Cowan for the newly created SFU. Baker served as the University's Director of Academic Planning and as the first head of the English Department. He remained at SFU until 1969, when he was appointed to be the first president of the new University of Prince Edward Island (1969-1978). He continued to teach there as a professor until 1991, when he retired.
Baker served on numerous councils and committees throughout his career, including the Canadian Association of University Teachers (1954-1969), the Royal Society of Arts (Fellow, 1971-1990), the Royal Commonwealth Society (1964-1966), the National Defence Strategic Studies Committee (Chairman, 1986-1998), the Canadian Executive Service Organization (CESO) (Volunteer Advisor to First Nations Groups, 1988-2004), and the Canadian Citizen Court (Presiding Officer, 1996-2004).
Baker was made an Officer of the Order of Canada (1978), and received numerous awards and honours, including the Queen’s Silver Jubilee Medal (1977), a Canada 125 Medal (1992), and the Queen’s Golden Jubilee Medal (2002). He also received honourary law degrees from the University of New Brunswick (1970), Mount Allison University (1977), University of Prince Edward Island (1989), and Simon Fraser University (1990).
published
Full
Revised
Title is based on the provenance of the fonds.
Fonds consists of records made and received by Ron Baker in his roles as academic planner, and charter faculty member, as well as additional materials relating to SFU's history. Includes personal and professional correspondence, reports, reference materials, a memoir by Baker about the early history of SFU, and other documents.
Original order was maintained by the Archivist where possible. Where no order was apparent, the materials were arranged by the Archivist.
Department of English; Photographic materials; Textual records; Buildings and structures
The fonds was donated by Ronald J. Baker to the Simon Fraser University Archives.
As of September 2009, all accessions have been processed. No further accruals are expected.
Please consult the inventory for the Office of Academic Planning, F-49.
Files marked 'pending review' must be reviewed by an archivist prior to release, and as a result of the review access restrictions may apply. Please see the file lists and consult the archivist for more details.
Series descriptions and file lists are available. An autobiographical sketch by Ron Baker is available in the hard copy version of the finding aid maintained in the Archives Reading Room.
- Personal correspondence, 1959 - 1997; F-34-1; 37 cm of textual records
  published
  Series consists of personal correspondence between Frances M. Frazer and Ron Baker. Includes day-by-day accounts of the writing of the Macdonald Report and the planning and beginnings of Simon Fraser University.
  No further accruals to the series are expected.
  Open
  A file list is available.
  - Personal correspondence - Baker to Frazer, 1959 - 1960; F-34-1-0-0-1 (Archival box - standard 34-1)
    Textual records
  - Personal correspondence - Frazer to Baker, 1960; F-34-1-0-0-2 (Archival box - standard 34-1)
  - Personal correspondence - Frazer to Baker, 1960; F-34-1-0-0-3 (Archival box - standard 34-1)
  - Personal correspondence - Baker to Frazer, 1961; F-34-1-0-0-4 (Archival box - standard 34-1)
  - Personal correspondence - Frazer to Baker, 1961; F-34-1-0-0-5 (Archival box - standard 34-1)
  - Personal correspondence - Baker to Frazer, 1961; F-34-1-0-0-6 (Archival box - standard 34-2)
  - Personal correspondence - Frazer to Baker, 1961; F-34-1-0-0-7 (Archival box - standard 34-2)
  - Personal correspondence - Frazer to Baker, 1962; F-34-1-0-0-8 (Archival box - standard 34-2)
  - Personal correspondence - Baker to Frazer, 1962; F-34-1-0-0-9 (Archival box - standard 34-2)
  - Personal correspondence - Baker to Frazer, 1962; F-34-1-0-0-10 (Archival box - standard 34-2)
  - Personal correspondence - Frazer to Baker, 1962; F-34-1-0-0-11 (Archival box - standard 34-2)
  - Personal correspondence - Baker to Frazer, 1963; F-34-1-0-0-12 (Archival box - standard 34-2)
  - Personal correspondence - Frazer to Baker, 1963; F-34-1-0-0-13 (Archival box - standard 34-2)
  - Personal correspondence - Frazer to Baker, 1963; F-34-1-0-0-14 (Archival box - standard 34-2)
  - Personal correspondence - Baker to Frazer, 1964; F-34-1-0-0-15 (Archival box - standard 34-3)
  - Personal correspondence - Frazer to Baker, 1964; F-34-1-0-0-16 (Archival box - standard 34-3)
  - Personal correspondence - Frazer to Baker, 1964; F-34-1-0-0-17 (Archival box - standard 34-3)
  - Personal correspondence - Baker to Frazer, 1965; F-34-1-0-0-18 (Archival box - standard 34-3)
  - Personal correspondence - Frazer to Baker, 1965 - 1970; F-34-1-0-0-19 (Archival box - standard 34-3)
  - Personal correspondence - Naming of SFU, 1981 - 1997; F-34-1-0-0-20 (Archival box - standard 34-3)
- SFU correspondence and subject files, 1963 - 1988; F-34-2; 25 cm of textual records 27 photographs: slides 7 photographs: prints 7 postcards; Physical description: 27 photographs: slides, 7 photographs: prints located in SMI Room 35-4-3
  While still a faculty member at UBC, Baker became one of the chief contributors to John B. Macdonald's report, Higher Education in British Columbia and a Plan for the Future. This report led directly to the government's decision to establish a second university (SFU) in the Lower Mainland. Baker also served on the provincial Academic Board for Higher Education, established to advise the government on applying the recommendations of the Macdonald Report.
  Records in this series relate to Baker's work on the Macdonald Report and the Academic Board as well as his role as academic planner and a charter faculty member in the early years of SFU. These files supplement the official records of the Office of Academic Planning, F 49. Includes personal and professional correspondence, reports, reference materials, a memoir by Baker about the early history of SFU, and other documents.
  Macdonald, John B.
  - Correspondence - general, 1963 - 1981; F-34-2-0-0-1 (Archival box - standard 34-4)
  - Correspondence - general, 1966 - 1973; F-34-2-0-0-2 (Archival box - standard 34-4)
  - Correspondence - general, 1984 - 1985; F-34-2-0-0-3 (Archival box - standard 34-4)
  - Macdonald Report, 1963 - 1971; F-34-2-0-0-4 (Archival box - standard 34-4)
  - General information on Colleges, specific on SFU regarding architectural plans and general concepts 1/2, 1964 - 1965; F-34-2-0-0-5 (Archival box - standard 34-4)
  - General information on Colleges, specific on SFU regarding architectural plans and general concepts 2/2, 1964 - 1965; F-34-2-0-0-6 (Archival box - standard 34-4)
  - Correspondence - publications ordered for SFU, 1964; F-34-2-0-0-7 (Archival box - standard 34-4)
  - Academic Board, 1964; F-34-2-0-0-8 (Archival box - standard 34-4)
  - Academic Board, 1964 - 1967; F-34-2-0-0-9 (Archival box - standard 34-5)
  - SFU Faculty, 1966 - 1981; F-34-2-0-0-10 (Archival box - standard 34-5)
  - CAUT Censure, 1968 - 1970; F-34-2-0-0-11 (Archival box - standard 34-5)
  - Letters of Congratulations, 1968 - 1975; F-34-2-0-0-12 (Archival box - standard 34-5)
  - PSA crisis, 1964 - 1970; F-34-2-0-0-13 (Archival box - standard 34-5)
  - History of SFU, 1968 - 1985; F-34-2-0-0-14 (Archival box - standard 34-5)
  - Testimonials regarding Ron Baker, 1977 - 1978; F-34-2-0-0-15 (Archival box - standard 34-5)
  - Clippings and publications, 1965 - 1988; F-34-2-0-0-16 (Archival box - standard 34-5)
  - Photographs and postcards, vol. 1, 1964 - 1967; F-34-2-0-0-17 (Archival box - standard 34-7)
    Photographic materials
  - Photographs and postcards, vol. 2, 1964 - 1967; F-34-2-0-0-18 (Archival box - standard 34-7)
- Academic Planning files, 1948 - 1970; F-34-3; 13 cm of textual records
  Series consists of records relating to the activities of Ron Baker as academic planner for Simon Fraser University. Series includes correspondence, statistics, agendas, minutes, publications and other documents.
  Some files may contain personal or confidential information. Access to these files may be restricted as stipulated by Archives policy or the donor. Files marked 'pending review' must be reviewed by an archivist prior to release, and as a result of the review access restrictions may apply. Please see the file lists and consult the archivist for more details.
  - UBC registrations, 1948 - 1964; F-34-3-0-0-1 (Archival box - standard 34-6)
    Pending review
  - UBC studies, 1958 - 1964; F-34-3-0-0-2 (Archival box - standard 34-6)
  - Enrollment, 1963 - 1965; F-34-3-0-0-3 (Archival box - standard 34-6)
  - Academic Planning - general, 1964 - 1965; F-34-3-0-0-4 (Archival box - standard 34-6)
  - Memoranda from Presidents to Heads of Departments, 1964 - 1965; F-34-3-0-0-5 (Archival box - standard 34-6)
  - English department at SFU, 1965; F-34-3-0-0-6 (Archival box - standard 34-6)
  - Humanities Research Council, 1965; F-34-3-0-0-7 (Archival box - standard 34-6)
  - Salaries, 1965; F-34-3-0-0-8 (Archival box - standard 34-6)
  - Student paper, April 1965 - October 1965; F-34-3-0-0-9 (Archival box - standard 34-6)
  - Three Universities Graduate Committee, 1965 - 1967; F-34-3-0-0-10 (Archival box - standard 34-6)
  - Humanities Association, 1966; F-34-3-0-0-11 (Archival box - standard 34-6)
  - Joint Faculty meeting, 1966; F-34-3-0-0-12 (Archival box - standard 34-6)
  - Student Implementation Committee report, 1968; F-34-3-0-0-13 (Archival box - standard 34-6)
  - Michael Bawtree re SFU Theatre program, 1969 - 1970; F-34-3-0-0-14 (Archival box - standard 34-6)
  - Architectural drawing of Academic Quadrangle - Zoltan Kiss, 1964 - 1965; F-34-3-0-0-15